[Anita] okay uh welcome to MagNetZ um this seminar is
recorded and gonna be made publicly available on
our YouTube channel continue participation
seminar of the recording begins constitute
agreement for the recording to be available on
YouTube and please keep your microphone muted
and turn off your camera if you don't want to be
seen or heard um the MagNetZ team welcomes you uh
it's it's gonna be continuing hopefully
uh the seminar series the format is
usually is about 25 minutes of presentation
followed by 15 minutes about of discussion
and there's going to be time for
catch-up in the end that is not recorded
um so for today I'm really happy to introduce
you Eric Font from University of Coimbra Portugal
um Eric is going to present a talk on magnetism
speleothems advances and perspectives so please
Eric take it up and share your
screen thank you very much
[Eric] okay it works [Anita] yeah we can see well thank y
ou thank you Eric [Eric] okay so the Earth magnetic field varies
in direction and intensity on the scale of ten to
ten thousand of years which is called the secular
variations and over geological times paleosecular
variation is recorded by rocks and igneous rocks
I recall the Earth's magnetic field through the
acquisition of Thermal Remanent Magnetization
but this only provides a snapshot of the Earth's
magnetic field on the other end sedimentary rocks
provide almost continuous record continuous
times for the other but suffer of a number of
limitations including diagenesis remagnetization
and inclination shallowing due to compaction
purely researchers like Alfred Latham
from the University of Liverpool investigate
uh the stalagmite uh the paleomagnetic record of
stalagmite with the aim of finding an alternative
continuous magnetic record indeed speleothems are
stalagmite deposits that grow almost continuously
and where magnetic particles inherited from
the upper soils and bedrock are transported
by drip water and deposited on the surface
of the speleothem acquiring Detrital remanent
magnetization so this this magnetization is no or
later affected by post postdepositional
processes and can be dated with a precision using
gradual isotopic series like uranium thorium
so after the work of Latham a number
of studies has been published in
this is only some two or two examples
um from Morinaga in 1992 Openshaw 1997
but this stopped in the end of in the end
of the 19th and we have to wait for uh 2011
with uh with the review paper by Ioan Lascu and
Feinberg to assist to a revival of the magnetism of
speleothems since and during the last decade um
several authors report an unprecedented record
of geomagnetic excursions in speleothems this is the
case for example the Blake geomagnetic exclusion
recording the radiometrically well dated
speleothem from Spain by Osete and colleagues in 2012.
this is also the case for the Lashamp excursion dated
with a precision by last Lascu and colleagues in 2016
at around 41 000 years uh or another
example of several geomagnetic excursions
recorded in a stalagmite from Italy in the
lower Brunhes magnetic chrom by Pozzi et al. 2019
the magnetism of speleothems can also
provide precious information about climate
and environmental change and this is a case for
example of the paper by Mark Bourne and colleagues
from 2015 where the outer show a nice
correlation between magnetite content
here illustrated by the flux of Isothermal
Remanent Magnetization with climate proxy
this is Oxygen and Carbon isotope composition
and here the concentration in magnetite
correlates with with this climate proxy and may
inform about variation in paleoprecipitation
this is another example from a spelelothem from uh
the Pau d'Alho cave in in Brazil by Plinio Jaqueto
and colleagues in 2016 where also the author
show nice correlation between concentration
concentration dependent magnetic proxies
with oxygen and carbon composition the author
interprets this correlation and
the concentration and the variation in
the concentration of magnetite uh controlled
by soil soil erosion and vegetation cover
more recently Yuval Burstyn and colleagues
studied the stalagmite from the Soreq
cave in Israel and also show a striking
correlation between magnetite content
and carbon isotope composition and the author
interpret this variation in magnetite content
as a result of variation of
rainfall and soil erosion
and thanks to recent technological advances like
scanning SQUID microscopy he developed and applied
by the research team of the MIT including Benjamin
Weiss and the Eduardo Lima we it is now possible to
study the magnetization of very fine calcite
laminae at the scale of 150 micrometers
this is an example of a paper by
Josh Feinberg he select several
magnetically enhanced layers using
screen scanning scanning screen microscopy
and based on precise U-Th dating the author
was able to reconstruct paleoflood events
and discuss the implication in term
of historical land use in Minnesota
another technique is a quantum diamond microscope
which provides mapping of the magnetic fields
at the micrometer micrometer scale this is a
paper by Roger Fu he investigate the power value
statement and the relation or correlation between
magnetic property and climate climate
proxy at a really really fine scale
so these are only some examples but the number of
paper about magnetism of speleothems published in
the last decade testify of the strong potential
of spelothems in providing outstanding data
for paleoclimate and Earth's
magnetic field reconstruction
so this this sounds like we are living in a you
know wonderland where everything is perfect and
works very well but but this is not actually
always the case and there indeed some problems
problem number one is whether speleothems can
experience depositional inclination error
Pioneer studies suggests that there
are no significant difference
between the acquisition of remanence in
the central or lateral area of a speleothem
however a recent paper by Jorge Pnte and
colleagues who study stalagmite from Algarve south
of Portugal demonstrate convincingly that
depositional inclination error may actually occur
so after adapting the standard amount using
U-Th and C14 we compare the magnetic direction
measured in several line and column with a
paleosecular variation model here's a SHADIF model
and we can see that the steeper the calcite layers
are the lower the magnetic inclination is so this
suggests that indeed some inclination error
may actually happen and you can see also this here
when looking at different line the same
calcite layer from a point located at the top and
A3 or a point located at the base A3 was the
inclination of the basal layer is different you
have almost five degrees of difference in the
magnetic inclination which is quite significant
so what we did here we did not have the
horizontal layer in this stalagmite but what
we did is to calculate the mean slope based
on this trend line for each line and we apply
this slope to all the data set here in B and we
interpolated the data to a deep count side of
zero this means for horizontal layer to obtain
the hypothetical values of magnetic inclination
for horizontal layer and after doing this we can
see that now they fit quite well with the model
okay also we are a little bit shallower a
little bit lower but still included in the
confidence interval of the model so we try
to investigate this effect by using anisotropy
and here this is that of anisotropy of magnetic
susceptibility and previous studies show that
natural and scientific car site um
the fabric is is dominantly oblate
and in the case of speliotime having
few or know the triple component
the k3 is perpendicular to the surface of the
spelling and corresponds to the direction of
the crystallographic axis of the calcite crystal
this is well illustrated here with a very strong
correlation between the k the orientation
of the k3 with the deep of the calcite layer
now if you if we want to look at so so in this
case the the fabric the ams fabric is dominantly
carried by calcite now if we want to look at
the ferromagnetic mineral we have to use an
anisotropy of anesthesia magnetization and
also the correlation is low moderate we can
see here trend and the correlation between
the k1 and the deep of the causal player
um when when you have paramagnetic or
ferromagnetic minerals the fabric is
is usually prolate and perpendicular perpendicular
to the to the surface to the stratification plane
um so what we can verify here is um
uh when when uh while the k1 of the
a of the of the ferromagnetic fabric
decrease uh concomitantly with the decrease
of the magnetic inclination and this indicates
that indeed magnetic minerals are our role
during the transportation along the stalamite
or um just mimic the shape of the star amount and
this leads to a change and and depositional error
in the inclination is a magnetic inclination
depending if you're on the top or on the border
so we try also to to check this effect um this
is not yet published data but this is a work
uh currently called by eliza sanchez mourinho
for the university of burgos in spain with the
skyline mind from the luger dos mercedes cave in
portugal and if we look at the horizontal layers
central growing axis we can see that for clean
layer dominantly calcite the fabric is oblate
and k3 is perpendicular to the stratification
plane now looking at more dirty and morally in
the sense that they contain more clay and digital
fraction and that's more ferromagnetic mineral
the fabric is prolate and k1 is
perpendicular to the stratification plate
now if you look at all the latter you got
mixture of fabric and intermediary fabric
depending on the relative contribution of
ferromagnetic mineral versus calcite so this is
this is an agreement with some outer previous
report when observing that um ims fabric can
change from able a oblate to prolate depending
on ferromagnetic or paramagnetic mineral are
at mix and if they overcome the signal
overcome the negative susceptibility of calcite
okay so uh now looking at oh this is
yeah this is the anesthesia anisotropy
of anesthesia magnetization and as in the case
of the bonds the statements followed by a point
the fabric is prolate and the k1 is
perpendicular to the stratification plane
now if you look at the inclined incline layers
layer abc these are the data of anisotropy
and we can see that there is a gradual change
in the orientation of k1 in the asm or air m
and this is actually the orientation of k1 in
this case very thin function of the deep of the
console's later so this is these are really
exciting data because you we can see that
the k1 almost mimics the shape of the stalagmite
this is almost a perfect uh fit between between
the shape and and the orientation of the k1 of
all the fabrics and of course if you look at
magnetic inclination it varies also accordingly
so this confirms that depositional inclination
error actually exists and this means that for
people who want to study stereotype in the future
we always have to focus on horizontal layers
essentially but this leads to problem number two
which is sampling because sampling is challenging
you need bravery and not to be claustrophobic
you also need a little bit of inventiveness to
orientate your sky might um but with time we
this is the most suitable technique we we find by
marking the north with the magnetic compass at the
at the top of the stalagmite and then using
the rubber bands and and the matter of seawing
and the level we report the mark
of the magnetic north on the border
and then cutting in the lab cutting is
the lamb is probably the most tricky step
it's like happening your kinder eggs because you
never know what you will got inside just before
to cut and you can have some surprise actually so
if you are lucky and get this kind of of spell out
where you have a nice uh horizontal layer along
the same drawing axis some of them may actually
um displaced driving axes so the growing axis is
not necessarily at the same place so you have to
play with several slides to be sure to have the
horizontal layer this is even more evident here
in this small one when the drip order displays on
the left and then you have to sample two different
slides and if you have to this the 3d perspective
this is even more complicated because for example
in this case it's okay you have a horizontal
wall on the front side and on the on the lateral
but if you look here you will see that you will
have a big problem because your your center
will not only include this layer but will only
include more youngest youngest layer here and
strongly in steep layers so this is definitely
not suitable another problem is uh the central
um axis dissolution this is a common future
in spellcam where you can have axial hole
due to low calcite deposition or both depositional
dissolution and if you look at these blocks you
can see nice uh nice pasta lamia but if you go
deeper and you will see that it's a mess because
you have this dissolution axis with probably
secondary calcite and so the orientation of
the magnetic mineral are not anymore the same as
the original calcite layer you want to study so my
tip is to cut spell time like you pin an artichoke
by doing several sides step by step slice by slice
until you reach some the less disturbed part and
by doing this you will also have several slides
that you can use for this different analysis
isotope isoprene as black indian p mac
uh problem number three is um the antagonism
between dirty and and clean started mine during
the census they contain a high concentration of
detrital mineral so this kind of stalagmite are
really good for for panel mag because you can
see really high magnetization really nice vectors
but there are nightmares for that in because
they contain a lot of detritorium which is a
contamination for for uth on the other
end clean stalagmites are very good for
for darling for radio isotopic darling
but you can have some surprise due to
really low magnetic content and have
this this really bad magnetic results
so a perspective is uh we developed an
approach recently this is a paper under
review by eliza sanchez moreno where we tried
to take spell outing using palu magnetic data
so we studied a star match from sofrador
carvalho in the central region of portugal
we dated by using uth and c14 and
provide the following age model
uh we conduct alternative field demagnetization
and terminology magnetization and obtain stable
well-defined and well-trusted characteristic
criminal magnetization direction
so this is age model based on radioisotope
data and their idea is to look and to search
for the best fit between our paleomy data here
in black and grey with a known uh polio circular
variation model in this case this is the shadif
model so we use the rakio dating matlab tool
by pavon karasco ital 2011. and actually he the
software is looking for the best fit between
the data of each sample and uh the reference
curve and then calculate the age and by doing
this we obtain the following edge model when we
compare this model with radioisotopic data we can
show that it's it's quite similar it fits quite
well also the paleomagnetic model has a higher
resolution due to high number of data points
but the mean age are more or less in the same
error margin and quite comparable we also try to
do this with the pay f m9k model from new zealand
and we obtain similar results also with some
differences but still in the confidence interval
um we also test the same approach in the star and
mic study by port and we also see that there is a
comparable age model that shares the same the
same confidence interval so this provide a new
approach to date stalagmite using paleomagnetic
data of course it has some drawbacks because
anyway you need at least an id of the age of the
stalagmite to choose the time window you will you
will select it for for the model and this can only
date young's period back to the last 14 000 years
because these are the limit of the available
biosecular variation model available in the
literature so to finish i will present
some preliminary data of a project
called samapa project founded by
foundation of science and technology
and also two collaborative uh project between
portugal and a19 usa uh this is uh uh the same is
the same stalagmite study by eliza the alien one
and these are the preliminary preliminary magnetic
data where we can show really nice geomagnetic
exclusion and uh this geomagnetic exclusion is
also recorded in a twin stalagmite located just
beside ln one and has the same pattern which is
gradual on the base and then absolutely come
back to normal to normal polarity at the top
this is a screen microscopy analysis produced
by eduardo lima from mit from a slice
or cut by diamond wire saw and here is the
representation of the natural remaining
magnetization after removal viscous
overprint and we can see area with high
rich magnetic mineral all that contain
strong magnetic records we also conduct fork
for jagram in all along the stalagmite
and it seems that the there is a stable
grain size distribution and composition of
the magnetic mineral throughout the entire
stalagmite which is uh dominantly carried
by single domain and and vortex state drains
and this is uh to finish i don't know uh the
time i hope i i have not exceeded the time
but this is um another experiment
which is uh done also by anarcho brass
in the frame of his master master tesis um the
question is whether we can find any indicator of
the digital input in in stalagmite i mean
how dirty how the style might hinge because
usually you can conduct in x-ray diffraction
but x-ray diffraction in installment is tricky
because you have more than 90 95 percent of
calcite and so the calcite peak dominates
most of the silo if you want to do icp mias
it's a little bit complicated because you have
to dissolve all the calcite um so we try to use
mercury why mercury because macrov is normally
carried by organic matter and clay and so it can
provide an indicator of of digital content and
here we can see a nice correlation between the
intensity of the natural remnant magnetization
which in part is controlled by the concentration
of magnetic mineral and the content is in in macro
okay so some conclusion and perspective so yes
we can say that fellow 10 can be considered
excellent recorder of the earth's magnetic
field and climate but with some caution
uh which is that depositional inclination
error may exist and more investigation is is
surely needed to understand how how this work
and how we can be able to correct this effect
um for people who want to study spanish
horizontal layer are the key so think twice
before cutting your stalagmites dirty versus
clean spell 10 this is a compromise you have to do
and well not everything is perfect
studying spell them uh magnetism
it's not straightforward you need braver
perseverance and you'll need luck and to get nice
nice nice results thank you very much uh
for for uh looking at his presentation
thank you very much eric uh very nice presentation
thanks uh let's give eric a big round of applause
thank you thank you very much um so if there is uh
some question please ask it away or use the chat
to do so um no questions yes no
there is a question yeah okay
maybe they are typing it
uh jose yeah yeah thank you
you cannot mute yourself if you want
all right okay let's use your can you hear me
yes thank you oh yeah quit typing then well
hi eric a nice nice talk nice lecture and
uh oh we had an opportunity to talk a lot
about all this just recently was a pleasure
having you in our lap um i already asked
you a little bit this but you know if you
had to define what kind of magnetization
we're measuring in flowstones you know following
the conventional standard classification of stable
magnetization what what would you say what it's
a mix if so what percentage of the throttle
versus posted throttle versus chemical i express
mean little bit your feelings give thoughts about
the nature of the magnetization in this paleo
themes at least the ones that you've measured
what's your sense well yeah yeah i
uh thank you joseph yeah we already
uh uh discuss about this and yeah in flosstown
i i'm i i do not really know about flawstones
there is some paper of flowstone i think it's
zanella from italia started flow stones and
my problem i would have with rose told this if
if if really the fabric of the magnetic mineral
um mimics the shape of the star and and if the
magnetization is detrital um this means that we
probably we have also some inclination um effect
on flowstone because because actually it's a slope
so when when the magnetic mineral that are
transported by the water along an inclined layer
so probably you will have some some effect um
but this is something that is that has never been
studied and and i mean you you got a lot of
flow still there and and you will probably
be able to look at this deeper and
now about your your other question
um well this is a good question because actually
this is something i'm wondering is uh many in most
of the of the spell cam and the data published
uh suggests that this is a digital magnetization
uh can we have really a chemical
magnetization this is a question because
i'm not sure this has this has been yet reported
in in in the literature um but in this case we
have to create new minerals and my my problem
is that cave conditions are quite stable and
very stable temperature is very stable um redux
conditions are stable in the absence of microbes
so yes maybe we can have some chemical
magnetization due to uh okay new new
magnetic mineral created and when they
reach the blocking volume okay they'll
require secondary magnetization um
but uh but yeah how how you created this this
secondary so okay a key is maybe microbes
because um microbe can be trapped within the
porosity of some skeletomine and there are micro
who has some affinity with iron and that can
dissolve magnetizing create new condition
and change the redox conditions so in this case
maybe they can be uh the agent to to to create
a secondary magnetization but i don't know all
of the paper i i know quite a lot of of it but
i i do not remember any paper demonstrating
your chemical magnetization in in star marks so
either it does not exist or simply that um it's
rare or people did not yet publish it but but
but yeah for me it's everything is that we
told until now and no chemical remagnitization
all right thanks eric thank you thank you
how to get back soon to your wonderful lab
and wonderful city anytime yeah thank you um
there is a question in the chat from jabuliu
nice talk i'm curious that whether the relation
between sampling position and inclination
shallowing could give some information about
the recording mechanism of nrm in stalagmite
let me see if i understand the
question i'm not sure to understand
uh where i can see the chat
okay let me open in the chat
uh well but this actually this actually what what
i tried to to show with um so so we see that the
fabric of ferromagnetic mineral is prolate and
in the data i show you see that the the k1 of of
the fabric of anesthetic remnant magnetization
is almost always perpendicular to the surface
so this mean probably that it's a definitory
magnetization okay because if it was a secondary
chemical you would not expect necessarily that
the magnetic the shape of the magnetic mineral
mimics the shape of the stalagmite okay if they
grew after the depositions on the calcite they
should not have this preferential orientation and
probably have i don't know same k1 direction but
okay the fact that the k1 of the anesthetic of the
anisotropy of anesthetic remnants magnetization
mimic and follow the deep of the calcite or i
mean the shape of the star might mean that the
magnetization is uh detrittle this is a sum of the
magnetic moment of the volume so this is the sum
of of the orientation of the different magnetic
particle okay and so i think this is a proof
that it's a detrital roman magnetization okay i i
don't know if i answer answer to your question but
but yeah okay okay yes thank
you for your question thank you
thank you um there is any other question
there is no other question then we can give
eric another big round of applause thank
you thank you very much very much and um yeah
i'm gonna share the screen for for the closing
statements uh we are currently in the
eu eastern uh industrial time slot
after august we are gonna go back to eu
western atmosphere time slot i'm gonna
take some break for meetings happening
during summer or winter during august
and on the 24th of august we are going to have
young lee from curry university in australia
and and then move back so stay tuned on our main
list and also please like and watch previous
uh talks and including this one on our youtube
channel thank you very much for for coming and
see you soon thank you very much thank you thank
you thank you les you can stop the recording now